Guide to the Rocket Press publications and ephemera collection, 1981-1994 MS2338
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Rocket Press publications and ephemera collection
1981-1994
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Rocket Press
Heller, Joshua
Stephenson, Jonathan (Printer)
Heller, Ralph
MS2338
3 Linear Feet Contains 4 document boxes and 1 oversized flat box
This collection contains various publications and ephemera printed by The Rocket Press from the personal collection of Ralph Heller. Ralph is the brother of Joshua Heller who, along with his wife Phyllis, established Joshua Heller Rare Books, Inc. in Washington, D.C. in 1985. The material in this collection dates from 1981 to 1994, and it provides a representative example of the work produced by The Rocket Press. The Rocket Press was a private British press started by Jonathan Stephenson in 1981 to create aesthetically unique and high quality printed material. Fine, small, or private presses are generally owned by an individual or small group and tend to publish items of distinctive content or form. These presses may focus on publishing unconventional writings, artists' books, illustrated literary texts, little magazines, and other unique items. Fine presses often generate limited runs of works that appeal to the tastes of the printer and a select audience, rather than producing items of broad commercial interest. Also characteristic of fine presses is meticulous attention to craftsmanship with regard to materials and process. Exceptional design as well as the use of premium or handmade paper, high quality inks, and traditional printing methods (such as letterpress) is often emphasized.
Arrangement
Organized into 2 series: Publications and Ephemera
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ralph Heller, April 14. 2015 (2015.026)
Biographical / Historical
From 1981 to 1994, The Rocket Press was one of the few modern private presses in Britain that operated full-time. The main function of the press was to create aesthetically unique and high quality letterpress books both under its own imprint as well as for other publishers. Ephemeral printing was also done to allow for new design challenges and to generate additional cashflow. Most notably, The Rocket Press was commissioned by McMillan Publishers, London, to print Sir John Tenniel's illustrations for Lewis Carroll's "Alice in Wonderland" and "Through the Looking-Glass" from the original 92 wood blocks which were discovered in the vaults of the National Westiminster Bank, Covent Garden, London, in 1985. The Rocket Press was started in 1981 by Jonathan Stephenson. Stephenson first started experimenting with printing at school at the age of eleven. Eventually, he set up his own workshop in his bedroom. By the age of sixteen, Stephenson had outgrown the space and moved his workshop into the stable house at his father's church in Steventon near Abingdon. It is in this location where he officially started The Rocket Press and published his first real books. In 1984, the press relocated to a corner of Steve Donoghue's former racing stables at Blewbury in Oxfordshire. Jonathan coordinated the entire printmaking process himself. However, he also enlisted the help of his brother, David, for folding and editorial work as well as Mr. John Bowley of the Oxford University Press for hand-setting and page make-up.
In 1994, Jonathan Stephenson shifted his focus to art and opened Rocket Gallery in London.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains various publications and ephemera printed by or about The Rocket Press of Jonathan Stephenson. The material dates from 1981-1994. The material is from the personal collection of Ralph Heller, brother of Joshua Heller who, along with his wife Phyllis, established Joshua Heller Rare Books, Inc. in Washington, D.C. in 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Bibliography: Rocket Press
Part One: The Steventon Books 1981-1985: 1981 The Art of Printing; 1982 The Shadow on the Plain; 1982 Shakespeare's Sonnets; 1983 Salute to Celia Fiennes; 1983 The Vacant Femme; 1983 Keble's Assize Sermon on National Apostasy; 1983 Nineteenth Century Trade Binding; 1983 A Posy of Wildflowers; 1984 Vines; 1984 Extracts from the Bermuda Gazette; 1984 Farewell to the True Bookshops; 1985 Private View
Part Two: The Blewbury books 1985:; 1985 Tract One; Bookish Quotations
Citation: An Offprint from The Private Library Volume 8:3 Autumn 1985
Private presses; Heller, Joshua; Heller, Ralph
- Publications, 1983-1993; Series 1; Heller, Ralph; Stephenson, Jonathan (Printer); Heller, Joshua
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This collection contains publications of stories, poems, articles, and images printed by or about The Rocket Press of Jonathan Stephenson. The material dates from 1983-1993. These publications are from the personal collection of Ralph Heller, brother of Joshua Heller who, along with his wife Phyllis, established Joshua Heller Rare Books, Inc. in Washington, D.C. in 1985. Authors represented in this collection include: John O'Connor, John Keble, John R. Smith, Tom Colverson, Dennis Hall, Noel Perry-Gore, Gwenllian Davies, John F. X. Harriott, Neville Braybrooke, Ray Howard-Jones, Lawrence Durrell, Edward Thomas, Jonathan Price, Merlin James, David Stephenson, John Russell Taylor, Jordana de Bijl, John Henry Newman, Robert Brough, Rev Dr Alan M. G. Stephenson, and David Burnett.
  - Ariel & Miranda by John O'Connor, 1992; Series 1; Boxed set of printed wood engravings engravings (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 8)
  - Assize Sermon on National Apostasy by John Keble, 1983; Series 1; Hardcover (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bookish Quotations by John R. Smith, 1985; Series 1; Paperback (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Catalogue of Fine Press Printers in the British Isles edited by Tom Colverson and Dennis Hall, 1986; Series 1; Paperback (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Christmas Sermon by Noel Perry-Gore [copy 1 of 2], 1985; Series 1; Boxed Hardcover (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A Christmas Sermon by Noel Perry-Gore [copy 2 of 2], 1985; Series 1; Boxed Hardcover (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Christmas Sermon by Noel Perry-Gore [2 copies], 1985; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Extracts from the Bermuda Gazette selected by Gwenllian Davies, 1984; Series 1; Hardcover (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Farewell to True Bookshops by John F. X. Harriott [3 copies], 1987; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fine Print, Vol. 14, No. 2, 1988 April; Series 1; Paperback (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Four Poems for Christmas by Neville Braybrooke [2 copies], 1986; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Heart of the Rock by Ray Howard-Jones [2 copies], 1993; Series 1; Hardcover copies (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Henri Michaux: The Poem of Supreme Solipsism by Lawrence Durrell [2 copies], 1990; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jonathan Stephenson & The Rocket Press by John R. Smith [2 copies], 1985; Series 1; Hardcover copies (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - An Offprint from The Private Library [2 copies], 1985; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Old Man by Edward Thomas [2 copies], 1990; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Private View by Jonathan Price [2 copies], 1985; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ray Howard-Jones: The Elements of an Art by Merlin James & David Stephenson [2 copies], 1993; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Robin Tanner: An Appreciation by John Russell Taylor [2 copies], 1989; Series 1; Paperback copies (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Salute to Celia Fiennes by Jordana de Bijl, 1983; Series 1; Paperback (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tract One by J. H. Newman, 1985; Series 1; Hardcover (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tract One by John Henry Newman, 1985; Series 1; Boxed Hardcover (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Vacant Frame by Robert Brough [copy 1 of 2], undated; Series 1; Boxed Set (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Vacant Frame by Robert Brough [copy 2 of 2], undated; Series 1; Boxed Set (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Victorian Archbishops of Canterbury by Rev Dr Alan M. G. Stephenson, 1991; Series 1; Hardcover (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Victorian Archbishops of Canterbury by Rev Dr Alan M. G. Stephenson, 1991; Series 1; Boxed Hardcover (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vines by David Burnett, 1984; Series 1; Boxed Hardcover (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Wood Engravings from La Vida Breve by John O'Connor, undated; Series 1; Paperback (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Ephemera, 1981-1994; Series 2; Heller, Ralph; Heller, Joshua; Stephenson, Jonathan (Printer)
  This collection contains various ephemera, including flyers, invitations, cards, illustrations, programmes, prospectuses, and poems printed by or about The Rocket Press of Jonathan Stephenson. The material dates from 1981-1994. This printed ephemera is from the personal collection of Ralph Heller, brother of Joshua Heller who, along with his wife Phyllis, established Joshua Heller Rare Books, Inc. in Washington, D.C. in 1985.
  - Address at the funeral of Lord Geoffrey-Lloyd by the Lord Charteris of Amisfield, 1984 September 17; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Alan & Betty Stephenson's silver wedding invitation, 1983 April 9; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Announcement: Limited edition od Lewis Carroll's The Hunting of the Snark with illustrations by Henry Holiday [2 copies], 1993; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Art of Printing by George Lovejoy, 1981; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Blackwell's Rare Books exhibition flyer, 1985; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Borlase Gallery exhibition flyers [2 copies of each], 1986; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Christmas cards and flyers, Circa 1984; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - A Christmas Sermon with engravings by Simon Brett, undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Edmund & Deborah Bennett's tin wedding invitation, 1985 August 2; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Fine Press Book Fair Catalogue [2 copies], 1990 October 13; Series 2 (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 1)
  - Flyer: Bookbindings at Horsham Book Shop, 1983 December 1 - 1984 January 31; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Flyer: Looking at Fine Printing [2 copies], 1989 March 8; Series 2 (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 4)
  - Flyer: Michaelmas Dance [2 copies], 1986 September 27; Series 2 (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 2)
  - Flyer: Relict's Relish [2 copies], 1986 October 18; Series 2 (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 5)
  - Flyer: Rocket Press of Jonathan Stephenson [2 copies], 1987 May; Series 2 (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 7)
  - Flyer: The Rocket Press stand at the American Booksellers Association Convention [3 copies], 1987 May; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Flyer: Selected Engravings of Krill Sokolov [2 copies], 1988; Series 2 (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 6)
  - Greeting Cards with illustrations by Richard Shirley Smith [2 cards], undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Informational flyers for The Rocket Press, Circa 1985; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Memorial address and program for funeral of Alan Malcolm George Stephenson, 1984 July 6; Series 2; 2 copies of memorial address (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Memorial address for Peter Wilson by the Earl Jellicoe, 1984 June 20; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Oxford Guild of Printers flyers, 1982-1984; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Oxford University Society of Bibliophiles programme of events, 1982; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Poem: A Calendar of Love by John Charles Edward Bowen [2 copies], 1983; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Poem: Rhodes & Asia Minor Remembered by John Charles Edward Bowen, 1983 October; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Prospectus: Sir John Tenniel's illustrations to Lewis Carroll's Alice's Adventures in Wonderland & Through the Looking-Glass, 1987; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Prospectuses for The Rocket Press publications [7], 1983-1985; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Publication Catalogue, 1994; Series 2 (Flat box 5, Oversize-folder 3)
  - Various Illustrations [4], undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 24)